Let's talk about what AI actually
is. So, what is a AI--well
actually this is a big discussion we
have to have
as a field--what is AI? Well, we're
going to be building machines, software,
you know,
that does something.
What's our goal, what does it mean to
build an artificial intelligence.
Well there have been multiple schools of thought on
this.
One school of thought is what we
should really be doing is building machines
that think like people, right. Intelligence is
about thinking, and this is artificial.
What's the natural intelligence--I guess
that's us.
So we want to build these machines that
somehow go through the thinking
processes that people do.
Alright, there is actually a science that studies this,
and it's not really AI anymore.
This is some mix of cognitive
science and computational neuroscience
really trying to understand the brain.
And it's very important but it's not what this
course is going to be about.
So another thing that people at times have
thought AI should be, is we should be
building machines that act like people.
Okay, so we should say: who cares
about how they think, they can think in some
strange, alien, silicon way, but the action,
the behavior has to be like what we know from people.
This is actually a very early definition.
This is straight from, uh, Alan Turing,
the definition that really, all you can
really do is check behavior. Is the behavior
like an intelligent human?
So this led to things like the Turing test where you put a robot on one
chat channel and a human on the other and
then you have an interrogator who chats
with both of them and tries to say that one
was the robot and that one was the human.
And this is a really good idea because
provided you can't actually see them--there's no
video right ..., where you know the robot's the one with the blinking lights right.
So provided it's just over chat
you can really kind of test anything.
It's open-ended: do they have hobbies,
can they answer a general question
about a chess configuration,
right. The problem was, the Turing test, in
order to really do well,
you don't just really concentrate on
programming intelligence, you concentrate
on things like,
don't spell too well,
humans don't do that. And so you build in
some type of typo Turing machines
and then you think, wait a minute, if i get
asked about the square root of thirty-five,
I better not have an answer.
And so you go through basically trying to
mimic things that probably you didn't
really value in the human in the first
place. On the other hand, you got to be
really sure that you have a favorite
Shakespeare play
'cause the interrogator always asked
that.
Okay, that's thinking like people and acting like
people and the realization was this
really wasn't going anywhere in terms of
building machines that were useful in
say industry,
and so the realization was maybe it's
not about mimicking people.
We've already got those, right. Maybe we
should do something else. Maybe what we should
be doing is building machines that think
rationally. So, whatever thought
processes are, they should be correct.
What does it mean to have a correct thought process,
it's a very kind of a prescriptive
thing.
And this actually has a long history in the
logicist and philosophy tradition
going all the way back, say to
Aristotle's laws of thought.
This is how you think
in order to kind of not make a mistake
in your deductions.
And this tradition actually still shows
up in various places of AI.
By and large,
this wasn't the winner, and the reason it
wasn't the winner is because our ability
to write down how to do logical
deduction
turned out to be relatively fragile,
and it any case when we're learning
about how to incorporate uncertainty we
also had this realization that really it
wasn't about how you think, but about the
actions you take in the end.
So the winner for this course is that AI, for us,
is the science of making machines, that act
rationally.
So what's that mean? We only care about what they do,
and our requirement on what they do is
the that they achieve their goals optimally.
You may be looking at this, and you maybe be thinking, okay rational, rational means I have a
level-headed decision, I don't get angry. So we want to build machines that don't get angry.
Well you know, I don't know, uh...
if you think back to GLaDOS maybe
that's good, maybe we shouldn't
build machines that get angry. Um... Skynet
got a little angry.
So maybe we shouldn't build machines that get angry.
But when we say rational that's not what we mean.
Rational has a very technical meaning. It
means that you maximally achieve your pre-defined goals.
So the input to an AI
is a goal,
and rationality means you achieve it in
the best possible way.
Rationality--only matters what you do.
It doesn't matter the thought process
you go through, right. If I have a
robot vacuum cleaner,
and it just makes some optimal grid on
the ground, and cleans up all the dirt, great.
If it sits in the corner and thinks, alright, where
shall I clean? Well if I go diagonally
there will be a place left over. And then
it cleans everything up--fine, it doesn't matter.
They're equally rational
for that task in that context.
There may be advantages to the thinking
robot,
there may be advantages to the kind of
more reactive reflex robot.
We'll talk about that in the next class.
Goals are all expressed through utilities. So
we're going to spend a lot of time in this course talking
about what a utility is.
And in the end remember that being
rational means maximizing your expected utility.
Okay, so this course, really, we should have called it computational rationality. We're going to teach you
computational methods--this is a computer
science course, and
it's all going to be about this idea of
rationality:
maximally achieving your goals.
Okay, you say what about artificial? I didn't really say anything about artificiality,
that's kind of orthogonal.
And what about intelligence? Well,
intelligence is a tricky thing. The
philosophers are still working on that.
When they get back to us on what intelligence is, well probably we'll just
ask them then what consciousness is.
but when they get back to us on
intelligence, we're gonna say,
that's great but we're working on rationality right now.
Okay, so if you remember nothing else in the
course,
or if you decide that you really want an AI tattoo,
and you needed to distill the course down to one thing,
it would be this:
it would be maximize your expected utility.
Aand we're gonna spend this entire course
thinking about computational systems
that do this.
And in order to do that we've got, you
know, however many weeks left in which we
will unpack this definition
The first part of the course deals with
the maximize:
How do I figure out which action is best?
That has to do with the consequences of
that action, the context of that action,
are there adversaries.
We're then going to have to unpack this idea of utility. What is utility?
What does it mean to have a function that
describes my goals.
And then, kind of the kicker in here
that's a little bit hidden is what is
this deal about expectation?
Well if I take an action I don't know
what's gonna happen.
So my optimization of goals
rationally doesn't deal being successful.
Life is full of risks. It has to do with
doing the right thing in kind of the
appropriate kind of weighted average.
And so we're going to have to unpack this
notion of what it means to do the right
thing on average, and that'll get us into
probabilistic inference, and that will
occupy the middle third of the course.